[Music]
from 1947 until 1952 the hooker Chemical
Company used the Love Canal section of
Niagara Falls as a dumping site for
toxic waste President Carter declared a
state of emergency today in the Love
Canal area of New York's Niagara Falls
where toxic chemicals were discovered
oozing from the ground that Discovery in
a Niagara Falls neighborhood triggered
an environmental battle that played out
on national television and became one of
the most iconic in US history
we we after the federal government
finally evacuated hundreds of families
new laws were introduced to prevent
Future Love canals ocidental Chemical
Company agreed to pay $129 million my
three kids were born with birth defects
my wife's had cancer more than three
decades later what happened to Residents
exposed to these chemicals and what
happened to the place that came to
symbolize the nightmare of toxic waste
in America
[Music]
in the spring of 1978 a Niagara Falls
housewife read a newspaper story about
her neighborhood known as Love Canal it
described 20,000 tons of chemicals
buried three blocks from my home that
these were very toxic chemicals and I
was just in shock the chemicals had been
dumped in an old Canal by the hooker
Chemical Company in the 1940s and early
1950s and then buried now they were
leaking into some of the homes closest
to the canal for several years chemicals
have been seeping into the basements of
a number of houses including this one
the evidence is always there there was a
report that talked about the different
chemicals getting into people's homes
getting into their Gardens their
backyards the people that were living
there were smelling these odors in their
basements many of the children claimed
that they had skin rashes and before you
know it there was a concern there have
been instances of birth defects and
miscarriages among neighborhood families
the state had been testing the
neighborhoods air soil and groundwater
and made an announcement for the homes
closest to the canal the New York State
Health Department recommended that
pregnant women and children under the
age of two immediately move out of the
area how many chemicals have been
identified as being underground here so
far we know of
88 specific chemicals that are that have
been identified and of those 88 how many
are suspected of causing cancer I think
the number is 11 you could see the fear
on some of their faces today as men
women and children gathered for blood
tests to determine whether those here
have developed abnormalities I am really
really afraid uh we have decided we're
going to get out one way or another but
right now you know you just can't jump
and where are we going to go go we were
a workingclass community we didn't have
money to just up and move and abandon
our house so we organized the Love Canal
homeown Association which was all of our
neighbors Lois Gibbs was trying to start
an organization and she quickly learned
how important the media was to be their
[Applause]
voice would you please tell me do I love
my three-year-old state New York
Governor Hugh Cary ordered the state to
buy the first two rows of homes along
the canal and those residents moved out
but Lois Gibbs and some 700 other
families living outside the evacuated
area were told they were not in imminent
danger they put up a
fence and every time I went in and out
of the driveway I seen the fence and I
was told that people on that side of the
fence had to leave and I had to
stay which didn't make sense to me at
all over the next 2 years some of the
remaining homeowners continued to battle
for relocation saying living near the
polluted Canal was putting their
family's health at risk I lost a baby
before it was even born my next door
neighor had is still
born her her son is sick her son is sick
how many more kids have to be sick some
of the protesters use provocative
tactics such as burning Effigies of
Jimmy Carter his wife and daughter today
the Environmental Protection Agency
announced but things changed in the
spring of 1980 the EPA had conducted a
preliminary study that indicated that
residents may have increased chromosomal
abnormalities but before the agency
could confirm the findings or inform the
residents the study was leaked EPA was
in a panic because they knew that this
uh awful chromosome study was going to
be hit the newspapers so they had an
emergency team rush out to Niagara Falls
to talk to these people we found two
particular characteristics
in this study which are ominous
enironmental Protection Agency had done
some blood work on some residents and
they said they had an unusually high
number of chromosome breakages and
higher risk of Cancer birth defects or
genetic damage in our children people
gathered at the Love Canal homeowners
office and they started shouting and
screaming so when when the EPA officials
came over um the residents were so angry
that they decided that if it's so safe
to live at Love Canal these two
officials can live here and they're not
going to get evacuated until we get
evacuated the standoff lasted just 5
hours but the point was made President
Carter was running for reelection this
was making headline news across the
country as a result of that sit in and
that protest and those hostage Holdings
the uh federal government agreed to
evacuate everybody at L Canal buying
their homes so we were out
the residents of Love Canal celebrated
today we got relief we got safety we got
we got our lives back 700 families
started leaving Love Canal this
afternoon it was the moment it was the
moment of relief and a sense that we're
free remember that we stood up up here
at Love Canal ordinary law-abiding
people and we weren't
afraid following the evacuation Gibbs
became the public face of a movement to
clean up toxic waste dumped by companies
across the country to deal with this
pollution super fund legislation was
enacted super fund was established so if
another Love Canal came on the horizon
there would be money there you could go
in you could do the testing you could do
the cleanup and then you could go after
the responsible parties while sometimes
criticized as costly and bureaucratic
super fund has led to the remediation of
near nearly 400 toxic sites Love Canal
was among the first addressed but it
took nearly 2 decades and cost more than
$350 million because the landfill turned
out to be too big too toxic and too
expensive to move it was capped in clay
and surrounded by a drainage system it
was a black eye when it occurred in the
late 70s but the community came together
and realized that the stigma from what
took place was starting to diminish so
in ' 88 a decision was rendered that the
area was suitable for rehabilitation the
city wants to put Love Canal behind it
it's given Niagara Falls a pretty bad
name and we don't think we deserve it
although the area around the old
landfill was fenced off homes in the
surrounding neighborhood were
refurbished and offered at below market
price nearly all the homes found a buyer
I just read about Love Canal you know up
in n
remember Love Canal 15 years ago they
had to move everybody out because of the
toxic waste now they're selling homes
there again I didn't I wasn't aware that
they're selling homes there don't you
think we could pick up something kind of
cheap the repopulation was met with
protest by activists including Lois
Gibbs who said the area was still not
safe they never took any chemicals out
the 20,000 tons of chemicals still
remain in the center of Love Canal I
think there's a legacy of Doubt because
people think that someday the landfill
will leak but we have monitoring wells
around this site so red flags would go
up if there was a problem the homes
around Love Canal especially the homes
that were rehabilitated where people
living in them today it's probably one
of the safest places on the planet to
live but what happened to the residents
who lived there 35 years ago the leaked
EPA reports was a preliminary study a
follow-up study revealed that Love Canal
residents had no higher rate of
chromosomal abnormalities than the rest
of Niagara County over the years some
Studies have indicated a higher rate of
birth defects and some cancers among
former residents but a direct link
between the leaking canal and the
long-term development of serious
diseases has not been established to
find out what hurt a relatively few
people because of the Myriad of
environmental insults that are around
it's almost impossible to do these are
intrinsically difficult problems to
evaluate
scientifically I was diagnosed with
pancreatic
cancer 3 years
ago and uh I'm stage four cancer it's uh
went to my
liver I worked with chemical
plants I was exposed to agent orange I
live in a Love
Canal I don't know where my cans are
come from
[Music]
35 years after Love Canal captured the
national Spotlight the story has
resurfaced new concerns have emerged
from the Love Canal era in 2011 a city
crew repairing a sewer line discovered a
pocket of chemical waste less than half
a mile from the landfill State and EPA
investigators said there was no danger
the waste was isolated had not leaked
from the landfill and was believed to be
left over from the original clean CLE up
but six families in the surrounding
neighborhood have filed lawsuits they
say the discovery exposed them to
harmful chemicals and now believe the
landfill itself is not properly
contained and is damaging their health
the battle over Love Canal continues
[Music]